A Guide to the Ross Family Correspondence, 1861-1864
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Ross Family Correspondence, 1861-1865
Library of Virginia
21089
.225 cu. ft. and 1 box
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Dr. J. Ross Perkins, Richmond, Virginia, on 22 January 1936
Biographical Information
James Ross (1791-1859) and Frances Hudson Loving Ross, married 22 February 1827) in Fluvanna County, Virginia, had six children. Their sons, James Eastin Ross (ca. 1834-1863), Nathaniel Wheeler Ross (ca. 1838- 1863), and William David Ross (ca. 1837-1863) enlisted in Company C, 14th Virginia Infantry at the beginning of the Civil War. James Eastin Ross was a carpenter before the war, Nathaniel Wheeler Ross a farmer, and William Daniel Ross a manager. James Ross and William Ross were killed in Pickett's Charge at the battle of Gettysburg on 3 July 1863. Nathaniel Ross died of disease two months earlier, 2 April 1863, at the Ross home, in Wilmington, in Fluvanna County. Their sisters Cornelia F. Ross, Lucy W. Ross (1848-1921), and Mary Eliza Ross (1828-1872) remained at home. Mary Eliza Ross married James White (1824-1905). Lucy W. Ross married Philip D. Perkins (1845-1915). One of their children was Joseph Ross Perkins (1877-1949) who graduated with a degree in dentistry from the Medical School of the University of Virginia. He resided in Richmond, Virginia. Perkins and his wife Maggie Parrish Perkins (1884-1973) had at least one child. Perkins is buried in Oakwood Cemetery in Richmond.
The sons of Pleasant White (1810-1869) and Martha Loving White, Richard Pleasant White (ca. 1840-1864) and Luther C. White were cousin of the Ross brothers. A sergeant in Company C, 14th Virginia Infantry, Richard P. White was wounded 10 May 1864 at Chester Station, and died of his wounds five days later on 15 May. Luther C. White served in the 22nd Virginia battalion and was captured in 1863 at Falling Waters, Maryland, and was released in February 1865. William P. Ryals (ca. 1842-1863) of Company C died of disease 25 February 1863. Benjamin C. Richardson (ca. 1834-1862), a farmer who enlisted in Company C was killed at the battle of Seven Pines on 1 June 1862.
Scope and Content
Correspondence, 1861-1864, of the Ross family of Fluvanna County, Virginia, consisting mainly of letters from James Eastin Ross, Nathaniel Wheeler Ross, William Daniel Ross, and their cousin Richard P. White, soldiers in Company C, 14th Virginia Infantry, to the Rosses' mother, Frances H. Ross, and sisters, Lucy W. Ross, Mary Eliza Ross, and Nela F. Ross. The Rosses and White describe camp life, including their health, food, clothing, religion, and guard duty. They recount the movements of their regiment from Jamestown, Virginia; Mulberry Island (now Fort Eustis) and Land's End in Warwick County, Virginia; to Suffolk, Virginia; to the Peninsula campaign, including the battle of Seven Pines (Fair Oaks) and the Seven Days Battles; from the Maryland campaign and the battle of Antietam (Sharpsburg) to the battle of Fredericksburg to the campaign leading to the battle of Gettysburg. They also comment on other battles both in and outside of Virginia, including: Big Bethel, Virginia; the West Virginia campaigns of 1861-1862; first and second Bull Run (Manassas); Lexington, Missouri; Burnside's North Carolina expedition; Fort Donaldson (Tennessee) Monitor-Merrimack fight; Corinth, Mississippi; Morgan's Kentucky raid of 1862; Murfreesboro (Stones River), Tennessee; Vicksburg, Mississippi; Chancellorsville; Brandy Station; and the battle of Winchester, Virginia, in June 1863. They also discuss the Trent Affair when the United States Navy removed two Confederate diplomats from a British vessel.
Letters comment on Union raids into Fluvanna County; the burning of Hampton, Virginia, by Confederate troops; a religious revival in camp; the use of African American labor in building fortifications and in company camps; and slaves in Fluvanna County. They mention various generals, including General John Magruder's ineptness; a brigade review by General George Pickett; the manuevers of General Jeb Stuart and his cavalry; the death of General Stonewall Jackson; and the military strategies of General Robert E. Lee. They mention President Abraham Lincoln and Union generals George McClellan and Joseph Hooker. Letters describe fraternization with Union troops while on picket duty and hopes for peace. They also discuss social life in Fluvanna County and in Richmond during the war. Other correspondents inlcude Callie Bragg, James Brainard Taylor Bragg, John Micajah Bragg, R. J. Bragg, Benjamin C. Richardson, William P. Ryals, and Luther C. White. Also includes a letter, 22 January 1936 from J. Ross Perkins, nephew of the Ross brothers and donor, giving information on the brothers' fate in the Civil War.
Arrangement
Arranged chronologically.
Contents List
- Correspondence, May-August 1861 (Folder 1)
  - Letter, 13 May 1861, from Nathaniel W. Ross, in camp in Richmond, Virginia, to his family and friends in Fluvanna County, Virginia, commenting on life in the army. Includes a postscript from William Daniel Ross., 1 leaf.
  - Letter, 16 May 1861, from Nathaniel Ross, Richmond, to his brother James Eastin Ross, Fluvanna County, describing his quarters, food, and military drilling., 2 pages.
  - Letter, 22 May 1861, from Nathaniel Ross, Richmond, to his brother James Ross, Fluvanna County, commenting on drilling and camp life, and describing an encounter between a U.S. Navy vessel and Virginia militia in Portsmouth, Virginia. Includes a postscript commenting on the company's weapons., 4 pages.
  - Letter, 27 May 1861, from William Daniel Ross (hereinafter Daniel), Richmond, to the Ross family, Fluvanna County, discussing a false report of a clash in Hampton Roads, and a rumor that his regiment will be heading to Fredericksburg or Manassas, Virginia., 1 leaf.
  - Letter, 28 May 1861, from Nathaniel Ross, Richmond, to his family, Fluvanna County, mentioning the rumored battle at Hampton Roads, discussing the preachers they have heard, and their orders to be prepared to move out., 4 pages.
  - Letter, 4 June 1861, from Daniel Ross and Nathaniel Ross, on Jamestown Island, Virginia, to their family, Fluvanna County, commenting on their health, the regiment's preparedness, lack of a post-office, and describing Jamestown and the James River., 3 pages.
  - Letter, 15 June 1861, from Nathaniel Ross, Jamestown, to his family, Fluvanna County, discussing the regiment's health, describing the island's fortifications and crops, mentioning the battle of Big Bethel, Virginia, and asking that he be sent tobacco., 4 pages.
  - Letter, 18 June 1861, from Nathaniel Ross, Jamestown, to James Ross, Fluvanna County, asking that he be sent some pantloons, and stating that Dick White would like some socks, drawers, and a waistcoat., 1 leaf.
  - Letter, 18 July 1861, from Nathaniel Ross, Jamestown, to his family, Fluvanna County, commenting on camp life, his enlistment, hopes for visiting home, and pay. He mentions a Confederate defeat in western Virginia (West Virginia)., 3 pages.
  - Letter, 24 July 1861, from Daniel Ross, Jamestown, to his sisters, Fluvanna County, concerning camp life, acquaintances at home and in the army, and news of the battle at Manassas, Virginia between Confederate and Union troops. He mentions the family's slaves., 3 pages.
  - Letter, 28 July 1861, from John Micajah Bragg, Camp Monterey, [Virginia], to his cousins commenting on army and camp life and food. He asks for letters., 2 pages.
  - Letter, 13 August 1861, from Nathaniel Ross, Warwick County, Virginia, to his family, Fluvanna County, discussing his regiment's movements and their first skirmish as the Confederates burned the town of Hampton, Virginia, 4 pages.
  - Letter, 19 August 1861, from Daniel Ross, Warwick County, to James Ross, Fluvanna County, discussing the regiment's new camp site at Mulberry Island and their hike there and provides news of friends. Mentions the African Americans there., 4 pages.
- Correspondence, September-December 1861 (Folder 2)
  - Letter, 1 September 1861, from Daniel Ross, Warwick County, to James Ross, Fluvanna County, discussing their camp and their closeness to the ships of the United States Navy in Hampton Roads. He also mentions friends in the regiment., 2 pages.
  - Letter, 8 September 1861, from Daniel and Nathaniel Ross, Warwick County, to their family, Fluvanna County, discussing their activities and marches. They mention several acquaintances., 2 pages.
  - Letter, 23 September 1861, from Daniel Ross, Warwick County, to James Ross, Fluvanna County, concerning camp life and friends., 2 pages.
  - Letter, 6 October 1861, from Daniel Ross, Warwick County, to James Ross and Lucy Ross, Fluvanna County, conerning camp life; a Confederate victory in Lexington, Missouri; and asking for items. He asks James to remember him to the slaves., 2 pages.
  - Letter, 23 October 1861, from Nathaniel Ross, Warwick County, to his sister, Fluvanna County, sending news and thanking her for items sent. Notes that there has been no skirmishes in the area, but he and his company are ready., 4 pages.
  - Letter, 17 November 1861, from Richard P. White, Warwick County, to his cousin, Fluvanna County, discussing camp life and wishing he could get a furlough to return home for a while. He mentions acquaintances at home and in camp., 3 pages.
  - Letter, 18 November 1861, from Nathaniel Ross, Warwick County, to his family, Fluvanna County, discussing another camp move by his regiment, and other news of friends and family., 4 pages.
  - Letter, 1 December 1861, from Nathaniel Ross, Warwick County, to his sister, Fluvanna County, sending news of camp, family, and friends. He mentions the blockading vessels of the U. S. Navy., 4 pages.
  - Letter, 8 December 1861, from Daniel Ross, Warwick County, to James Ross, Fluvanna County, commenting on his health, his regiment's movements, and a skirmish between a Confederate vessel and Union ships. He also comments on fighting in South Carolina and Florida., 3 pages.
  - Letter, 14 December 1861, from Richard P. White, Warwick County, to his cousin, Fluvanna County, remarking on camp life and news of family and friends., 4 pages.
  - Letter, 15 December 1861, from Nathaniel Ross, Warwick County, to James Ross, Fluvanna County, concerning camp life and mentioning the the Union blockade and a confrontation between the Patrick Henry, a Confederate vessel, and Union ships., 4 pages.
  - Letter, 26 December 1861, from Nathaniel Ross, Warwick County, to James Ross, Fluvanna County, sending camp news and news on family and friends. He mentions the Trent Affair., 1 leaf.
  - Letter, 29 December 1861, from Daniel Ross and Nathaniel Ross, Warwick County, to their family, Fluvanna County, sending camp news, asking for items from home, and mentioning a skirmish between Confederate and Union soldiers., 4 pages.
  - Letter, 29 December 1861, from Richard P. White, Warwick County, to his cousin, Fluvanna County, providing camp news and news of family and friends., 4 pages.
- Correspondence, January-February 1862 (Folder 3)
  - Letter, [?] 1862, from James Eastin Ross, [near Richmond?], to his family, Fluvanna County, containing news of the camp life of the company, including the news that the men hired an African American cook., 4 pages.
  - Letter, 6 January 1862, from Daniel Ross and Nathaniel Ross, Warwick County, to James Ross, Fluvanna County, sending camp and personal news. Nathaniel reports a box James sent him had been stolen. He mentions an exchange of prisoners between the Confederate and Union armies., 3 pages.
  - Letter, 15 January 1862, from Nathaniel Ross, Warwick County, to James Ross, Fluvanna, complaining of the continual movement from camp to camp and about General John Magruder. He comments on men hiring substitutes to fight, and notes that the culprits who stole the box were found., 3 pages.
  - Letter, 15 January 1862, from Daniel Ross, Warwick County, to James Ross, Fluvanna County, concerning his poor health, the company's new camp, and the stolen box. He mentions the continued excitement over the Trent Affair, and that Union troops under Ambrose Burnside have left Fort Monroe., 2 pages.
  - Letter, 2 February 1862, from Richard P. White and Nathaniel Ross, Warwick County, to Ross' sister, Fluvanna County, concerning their new camp. Nathaniel reports that he might not reenlist in his current company, but take a 30 day furlough and get an enlistment bonus of $50.00., 4 pages, incomplete.
  - Letter, 2 February 1862, from Daniel Ross, Warwick County, to James Ross, Fluvanna County, concerning the regiment's new camp, the battle of Mills Spring, Kentucky, the death of John Tyler, and the Ambrose Burnside expedition., 2 pages.
  - Letter, 9 February 1862, from Daniel Ross, Warwick County, to James Ross, Fluvanna County, discussing efforts to reenlist the 14th Virginia Regiment, reports that Burnside's expedition had failed, and war news from Tennessee., 3 pages
  - Letter, 16 February 1862, from Nathaniel Ross, Warwick County, to James Ross, Fluvanna County, discussing the fall of Roanoke Island to Burnside's expedition, efforts to reenlist Company C, 14th Virginia as a cavalry unit, and news of friends and family., 3 pages.
  - Letter, 19 February 1862, from Richard P. White, Warwick County, to Mary Eliza Ross, Fluvanna County, discussing camp news and efforts to reenlist the company. White hopes that James Eastin Ross will join the company., 3 pages.
  - Letter, 26 February 1862, from Nathaniel Ross, Warwick County, to James Ross ( Crack ), Fluvanna County, concerning his reenlistment and James' possible enlistment. He mentions the capture of Fort Donaldson., 4 pages.
- Correspondence, March-April 1862 (Folder 4)
  - Letter, 3 March 1862, from Daniel Ross, Warwick County, to James Ross, Fluvanna County, concerning Richard White's and Nathaniel Ross' reenlistment in the 14th Virginia. He discusses his concerns over Union victories in Tennessee and North Carolina., 4 pages.
  - Letter, 12 March 1862, from Richard P. White, Suffolk, Virginia, to his cousin, Fluvanna County, describing the regiment's relocation to Suffolk, mentioning the Merrimack's attack on the Union Navy, and discussing family and personal news., 4 pages.
  - Letter, 12 March 1862, from Daniel Ross, Suffolk, to his sister, Fluvanna County, informing her of the regiment's move to Suffolk, describing the Merrimack's assault on the Union Navy, and personal news, including his reenlistment., 4 pages.
  - Letter, 20 March 1862, from Benjamin C. Richardson, Suffolk, to Cornelia F. Ross (hereinafter Nela), Fluvanna County, saying how much he would like to see her and other friends at home., 4 pages.
  - Letter, 21 March 1862, from Nathaniel Ross, Suffolk, to his brother James Ross ( Crack ), Fluvanna County, concerning reenlistment and the draft., 4 pages.
  - Letter, 23 March 1862, from James E. Ross to his sister Mary E. Ross, Fluvanna County, commenting on his joining the 14th Virginia, and stating that he has little news., 2 pages.
  - Letter, 1 April 1862, from Nathaniel Ross, Suffolk, to his cousin, Fluvanna County, noting that nothing is happening and wishing that he could come home and visit with the ladies., 2 pages.
  - Letter, 6 April 1862, from Richard P. White, Suffolk, to his father, Fluvanna County, sending camp news and informing his father of his illnesses., 3 pages.
  - Letter, 11 April 1862, from James Ross, Suffolk, to his mother Frances H. Ross, Fluvanna County, describing his journey from Fluvanna County to Suffolk to join the 14th Virginia, and telling her that he has seen his brothers and cousins in camp., 2 pages.
  - Letter, 11 April 1862, from James Ross, Suffolk, to John Bragg, Fluvanna County, discussing his trip from Fluvanna County to the camp of the 14th Virginia in Suffolk, including a stop in Richmond to settle Bragg's bill with the Enquirer., 4 pages.
  - Letter, 17 April 1862, from Richard P. White, Suffolk, to his cousin, Fluvanna County, discussing camp life and his responsibility to drill a militia unit., 3 pages.
  - Letter, 17 April 1862, from Nathaniel Ross, Suffolk, to his mother Frances H. Ross, Fluvanna County, sending camp news and noting the possibility of a battle on the Peninsula., 2 pages.
- Correspondence, May-June 1862 (Folder 5)
  - Letter, 8 May 1862, from Nathaniel Ross, Suffolk, to his mother and sisters, Fluvanna County, informing them of the impending loss of Norfolk, Virginia, a battle on the Peninsula, a reorganization of the 14th Virginia, and Daniel's convalesence in Petersburg., 2 pages.
  - Letter, 14 May 1862, from Daniel Ross, Petersburg, Virginia, to his mother Frances H. Ross, Fluvanna County, concerning his convalescence in Petersburg., 2 pages.
  - Letter, 16 May 1862, from Callie [Bragg], Richmond, Virginia, to Nela Ross, Fluvanna County, sending family news and expressing her concern that the Union army is very close to Richmond., 4 pages.
  - Letter, 17 May 1862, from James Ross, Petersburg, to Frances H. Ross, Fluvanna County, informing her of the regiment's move from Suffolk to Petersburg and noting that he had little to eat while on the march., 4 pages.
  - Letter, 19 May 1862, from Nathaniel Ross, Petersburg, to Francis H. Ross, Fluvanna County, sending news of himself and his brothers, and stating that they are sending some clothing they don't need home., 3 pages.
  - Letter, 21 May 1862, from R. J. Bragg to his cousin and uncle discussing camp and personal news., 4 pages.
  - Letter, 26 May 1862, from James Ross to Frances H. Ross, Fluvanna County, stating that Daniel hopes to get a furlough and remarking on the fighting on the Peninsula and how Joseph Johnston's withdrawal up the Peninsula has upset many soldiers., 4 pages
  - Letter, 2 June 1862, from Daniel Ross, Richmond, to his sister, Fluvanna County, informing her of the 14th Virginia's first action during the battle of Seven Pines, including news of the death of Ben C. Richardson and James' wounding in battle., 3 pages.
  - Letter, 8 June 1862, from Nathaniel Ross, near Richmond, to Nela F. Ross, Fluvanna County, concerning the 14th Virginia, battle of Seven Pines and the death of Ben Richardson. He describes the location of the regiment's camp and mentions possible future battle., 3 pages.
  - Letter, 21 June 1862, from Nathaniel Ross, near Richmond, to Mary Eliza Ross, Fluvanna County, concerning Daniel's poor health and sickness among the company. He mentions a skirmish between Union troops and the 53rd Virginia and Stuart's ride around McClellan., 2 pages.
- Correspondence, July-September 1862 (Folder 6)
  - Letter, 10 July 1862, from Nathaniel Ross, Richmond, to Mary Eliza Ross, Fluvanna County, describing the Seven Days Battles, including the battle of Malvern Hill. He provides the regiment's casualties., 4 pages.
  - Letter, [?] July 1862, from an unknow correspondent to an unknown recipient containing camp news., 2 pages, fragment.
  - Letter, 24 July 1862, from Nathaniel Ross, near Richmond, to Daniel Ross, Fluvanna County, stating he hopes Daniel is feeling well, updating him of James' wound, and commenting on the decline of the regiment since Seven Pines., 4 pages.
  - Letter, 3 August 1862, from Nathaniel Ross to the Ross family, Fluvanna County, discussing camp news, whether the Union army will move on Richmond, and whether England and France will recognize the Confederacy., 3 pages.
  - Letter, 5 August 1862, from Richard P. White to his cousin, Fluvanna County, containing camp news., 3 pages.
  - Letter, 26 August 1862, from Nathaniel Ross, Fauquier County, to Daniel Ross, concerning the regiment's and army's maneuvering, and skirmishes with Union troops., 2 pages.
  - Letter, 5 September 1862, from Richard P. White, Loudoun County, Virginia, to his cousin, Fluvanna County, concerning the second battle of Manassas (Bull Run) and his regiment's movements., 2 pages.
  - Letter, 9 September 1862, from Nathaniel Ross, Frederick County, Maryland, to James Ross, Fluvanna County, concerning the Confederate army's move into Maryland and sending camp news., 3 pages.
  - Letter, 29 September 1862, from Nathaniel Ross, Frederick County, Virginia, to James Ross, Fluvanna County, describing the army's battle at Sharpsburg, Maryland (Antietam), and retreat. He adds that the army is tired and he hopes for peace., 3 pages.
- Correspondence, October-December 1862 (Folder 7)
  - Letter, 4 October 1862, from Richard P. White to nela F. Ross, Fluvanna County, sending camp news., 4 pages.
  - Letter, 6 October 1862, from James Ross and Nela Ross, Fluvanna County, to Nathaniel Ross informing him how Fluvanna County is suffering from the war in terms of the deaths of many of its sons., 4 pages.
  - Letter, 15 October 1862, from James Ross and Daniel Ross, Fluvanna County, to Nathaniel Ross, regarding crops in Fluvanna County, news of a battle at Corinth, Mississippi, John Hunt Morgan's raid in Kentucky, and the brothers' hopes for peace., 3 pages.
  - Letter, 3 December 1862, from Richard P. White and William P. Ryals to Nathaniel Ross, Fluvanna County, sending news of the company., 2 pages.
  - Letter, 26 December 1862, from James Ross, near Fredericksburg, Virginia, to Mary Eliza Ross, Fluvanna County, describing his return to Company C, 14th Virginia, in the days after the battle of Fredericksburg., 2 pages.
  - Letter, 26 December 1862, from Richard P. White, near Fredericksburg, to his cousin, Fluvanna County, sending camp news., 4 pages.
  - Letter, 30 December 1862, from Richard P. White, Guinea Station, Virginia, to Nathaniel Ross, Fluvanna County, stating that both armies apparently have gone into winter quarters and sending other camp news., 2 pages.
  - Letter, 30 December 1862, from Richard P. White, Guinea Station, to Luther C. White, Fluvanna County, sending camp and personal news. He doesn't believe there will be much fighting during the winter., 2 pages.
  - Letter, 31 December 1862, from Daniel Ross to his sister, Fluvanna County, concerning his health and his travel back to his company., 1 leaf.
- Correspondence, January-February 1863 (Folder 8)
  - Letter, 4 January 1863, from Richard P. White, Guinea Station, to his cousin, Fluvanna County, containing news of the company., 2 pages.
  - Letter, 5 January 1863, from James Ross, Guinea Station, to Frances H. Ross, Fluvanna County, sending camp news, asking where his brother Daniel is, enclosing news of the battle of Murfreesboro, Tennessee and of Vicksburg, Mississippi, and adding that he thinks peace soon come., 2 pages
  - Letter, 5 January 1863, from Daniel Ross, Huguenot Springs hospital, to his sisters, Fluvanna County, concerning his stay in the hospital and his belief that peace is near., 2 pages, incomplete.
  - Letter, 10 January 1863, from James Ross, near Guinea Station, to Nela F. Ross, Fluvanna County, sending company news., 2 pages.
  - Letter, 14 January 1863, Daniel Ross, near Guinea Station, to his sister, Fluvanna County, concerning his return to his regiment and their greetings. He notes that the Union army is north of the Rappahannock River., 2 pages.
  - Letter, 19 January 1863, from Daniel Ross, near Guinea Station, to Nathaniel[?] Ross, Fluvanna County, sending him company news, mentioning a rumor of a Union troop movement, and hoping that his brother will soon rejoin the regiment., 2 pages.
  - Letter, 26 January 1863, from Daniel Ross, near Guinea Station, to his sister, Fluvanna County, describing Fredericksburg, detailing picket duty there and conversations with Union pickets, and sending other news., 2 pages.
  - Letter, 10 February 1863, from James Ross to Mary Eliza Ross, Fluvanna County, discussing camp life and news., 2 pages.